When you put this into context and you
talk about the Saudi Pakistan mutual
defense pact that was just signed a few
months ago.
>> Yes.
>> Is Saudi Arabia basically calling in its
investment?
>> I think yes. But you know, I have to
laugh about this mutual defense pact.
I don't know if you've ever spent any
time in Saudi Arabia,
but almost the entire Saudi military
is Pakistanis.
No Saudi is going to join the military
unless they're going to make him a
general,
you know? There are a lot of Bedouins in
the Saudi military, but you go straight
in as an officer. If you're a Saudi
citizen, you're going to start as an
officer. There are no There are no
privates or corporals who are Saudi.
They're all Pakistani. All of them.
It's the Pakistanis that protect Saudi
Arabia.
>> But how realistic is a
>> On the on the ground.
>> But how realistic is a nuclear umbrella
though? That's what is I mean that the
at least some of the doomsayers in India
think of it like that.
>> Yeah, I don't think it is realistic.
>> Yeah.
>> No, I don't think it's realistic.
>> when this A.Q. Khan uh
thing happened and it was brought up,
what was this Saudi Arabia hold on
America? Now you have
Saudi terrorists
taking out the 9/11 towers.
>> That's right.
>> Saudi Arabia actively lobbying to
protect one of the most dangerous men uh
at least in the last quarter century at
least in this region.
And then eventually Pervez Musharraf
also pardoning A.Q. Khan, therefore
ending all investigations. What is this
function that America has with dictators
and this love story?
>> That is That is one of the most
difficult questions that you could ask.
You know, we we like to we like to try
to convince the world that we are a
shining beacon of hope for democracy and
human rights and equality and it's just
simply not true.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
our our foreign relations
um
our foreign relations are based on
on our national needs at any given
moment. We don't do things because
they're the right thing to do.
>> Mhm.
>> We do them because they happen to be
good for us that day.
Which is why we get into bed with so
many dictators around the world. Which
is why we get into bed with with so many
politicians who are so extreme in their
personal politics that it makes no sense
to the American people. Why are we in
bed with Benjamin Netanyahu right now?
When we've known Netanyahu since the
1980s as an extremist.
>> Yes.
>> Because it's uh
it's
it's the easy thing to do and it serves
our purposes, you know, today. That may
change tomorrow but but today it's okay.
You know, I I worked for an ambassador
in Bahrain who was an absolutely lovely
man.
And he he said one day, I still remember
this. I was young and impressionable and
he said, you know, our foreign policy in
in Saudi Arabia
really is as simple as
we buy their oil and they buy our
weapons.
>> That's it. That's it.
>> That's it. That's the basis. He said,
you spend your career in the Middle
East, I've spent my entire adult life in
the Middle East. He said, I don't like
the Saudis. They don't like us.
But we pretend to have this special
relationship.
Right? Even in the American Embassy I my
first overseas tour was in Saudi Arabia.
And I remember an enormous
photograph. It had to be 2 m across,
and it was President Franklin Roosevelt
and King
Abdul Aziz ibn Saud, the founder of
Saudi Arabia, in the back of a car
together. And this was supposed to be
emblematic of our special relationship
with the Saudis.
But,
when I first arrived in Saudi Arabia,
um
I was placed in um embassy housing. So,
I was living in in an apartment in the
diplomatic quarter, and I would walk a
block or two to the to the embassy and
go in the back entrance of the embassy.
And every day, my first 3 days, I would
say to this Saudi
guard, national uh saying Saudi Arabia
National Guard
uh officer standing there, "Salam
alaykum."
The response, of course, is "Walaykum
assalam."
>> Yes.
>> He would He would ignore me.
So, the next day, I went in and I said,
"Salam alaykum."
>> Mhm.
>> And he ignored me. The third day, I went
in and I said, "Sabah al-khair wa sala
assalam alaykum." "Good morning and
peace be upon you."
He ignored me, and I stopped and I said
to him, "What's your problem?"
And he said to me in English,
he said,
"You are hired help.
We paid for you to come here and defend
us. We are not friends."
>> Mhm.
>> And I said, "You know what?
You're right.
We aren't friends.
I don't like you,
and I don't like any of your
compatriots, none of them."
>> Right.
>> And then I never spoke to him again. But
that was the US Saudi relationship in a
nutshell.
>> Do you think Saudi Arabia knows this
now? Cuz
with this mutual defense pact, Again,
bring I keep coming back to the nuclear
thing and them sort of
you know, basically seeking nuclear
deterrence with the help of Pakistan.
Then it it appears with the new with the
with this uh Trump regime that a certain
amount of American retrenchment has
happened in the region where it's almost
almost like a hemispheric defense now
that America is focusing on. So, Saudi
Arabia always had the US for its back.
Now that US is not at least it appears
that it's not highly dependent on uh
Saudi oil, Saudi energy.
Do you think Saudi Arabia is doing this
as an insurance pact?
>> Absolutely, yes. And it's not just Saudi
Arabia, it's Kuwait as well. Kuwait last
year made a purchase of uh and I made a
purchase uh made a sale of oil to China
and for the very first time ever took
payment in yuan.
Yeah. First time ever that payment was
not in dollars. So, I think everybody is
coming around to the notion that here in
the United States we're sitting on an
ocean of oil.
Okay? We have shale oil enough to last
us 500 years. We don't need Middle
Eastern oil. We buy it
because it's good for relations.
>> Yes.
>> Because we we buy it and then they buy
our weapon systems.
>> Right.
>> So, we continue to do that. But but when
it when push comes to shove, we don't
need the Saudis anymore.
We don't.
Mhm. And so, they're hedging their bets.
They're they're improving their
relations with China. They're improving
their relations with India, which is a
huge market and in need of oil.
>> Yes.
>> And and you know, if the if the Indians
are going to have
problems especially from the United
States buying Russian oil or Russian
natural gas, they should just buy it
from Saudi Arabia. Makes it even easier.
>> Right. Yeah, absolutely.
>> So, I think we're we're seeing a
transformation here in in the the way
the world operates.
>> dynamic geopolitical shift is being
viewed here. That's why conversations
with you
uh someone in the field and who has
historical context. I mean it's it's
fantastic. You know, so we we had this
hot war with Pakistan in May and it
happened in the the nuclear question
came up again. And I thought what better
person than you to sort of, you know,
illuminate a little bit more about
Pakistan's nuclear weapons and
everything. So you were there on the
ground in Pakistan in 2002-2003.
We also saw Pakistan sort of lurch into
almost like a civil war with the various
terrorists it had propped up in its
backyard, you know, was there ever a
fear that these nuclear weapons would
fall into
a terrorist hands?
>> Yes.
When I was when I was stationed in
Pakistan in 2002, I was told
unofficially that
that the Pentagon controlled the
Pakistani nuclear arsenal.
That Musharraf had turned control over
to the United States because he was
afraid of exactly what you just
described.
But the Pakistanis in the intervening
years, and remember I was there 23
years ago.
Over the last 23 years, the Pakistanis
have come to say that is absolutely not
true.
The United States has nothing to do with
the Pakistani nuclear arsenal. That
Pakistani generals are the ones that
control it.
So I don't know if if that's true,
then I would be very worried about who
is in charge politically in Pakistan.
>> No.
>> You know, for for example, for example,
um
Imran Khan. I can't believe that I
forgot his name.
>> Who's in jail? A popular
Yes, yeah.
>> Right, and still wildly popular.
>> Wildly, yeah.
>> He told us when he was still the prime
minister, he said, "Listen, I've got
this political situation here
domestically. I'm going to start blaming
you for everything."
And and the ambassador laughed and said,
"We get blamed for everything anyway, so
we don't care."
So, everything that happened, it was the
United States' fault, and it was the US
they turned their backs on us, and the
US did this, and the US did that, and
then they arrested him anyway.
So, he got a message out to the US
government saying, "Can you help me get
out of this?"
And we went to Jemima Goldsmith, his
gold whatever her name was.
>> Ex-wife.
And she went to Pakistan and asked them
if they would release him, and they said
no.
So, like you, I'm worried about
continued
disagreement in Pakistani politics that
has the potential to spill into the
streets because the Pakistanis have a
tendency to get themselves spun up,
>> Mhm.
>> and people die during demonstrations,
and there are attacks against political
figures, and assassinations, and
and uh and the country is not known for
its uh transformative, you know, leaders
making positive decisions. I'll tell you
another thing.
When Benazir Bhutto was in exile
in uh Dubai,
>> Mhm.
>> um I went to see her with another a
senior officer. I went as the note
taker.
And um
she lived in this
$5 million
palace
on the on the Gulf.
And we were sitting in the the front
room, the the salon of of the house, and
we heard a car pull up.
And she said,
her exact words, "So help me God, if he
came home with another Bentley, I'm
going to kill him."
>> Is that her daddy?
>> Yeah.
>> Her husband.
>> And I said to my boss afterwards,
"She makes $60,000 a year.
She lives in a $5 million house and he
has a collection of Bentleys.
Aren't they ashamed of themselves? Like,
how can they go back to Pakistan and
look the Pakistani people
in the face when their people don't even
have shoes
and no food to eat?
Like, I understand corruption is a
problem there, but that level of
corruption?
Come on. Well, those are the kinds of
politicians that the people have to deal
with.
>> You talked about Benazir Bhutto. You
talked about Zardari. Zardari is the
current president over here.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, going back to the nuclear nuclear
issue, you know, in this war that
happened in May, India for the first
time escalated it to a level where we
had cruise missiles flying into
Pakistan with direct hits at the time.
And from the Indian side, this constant
line is
is said from right up from the prime
minister level up. He says that
that we called their nuclear bluff.
You said that you were told unofficially
that you knew that America knew where
the nukes were. Do you think Americans
told India that
the control of Pakistani nukes also lies
with America?
>> I doubt it.
I doubt it because of the vociferousness
with which
the Pakistanis have come out publicly
and said that they control the nukes,
but I can tell you definitively
that
the State Department was telling both
sides, "If you're going to fight, fight.
Keep it short and keep it non-nuclear."
If nuclear weapons are introduced, the
whole world is going to change. And so,
I think there was restraint on both
sides. The Pakistanis need to come to a
policy conclusion that there's nothing
positive for them in fighting India.
Nothing. Literally nothing good will
come of a of an actual war between India
and Pakistan because the Pakistanis will
lose.
>> Mhm.
>> It's as simple as that. They'll lose.
And I'm not talking about nuclear
weapons. I'm talking just about a
conventional war. The Pakistanis will
lose.
>> Right.
>> And so there's no benefit
to constantly provoking the Indians.
>> Right. Last question on the nuclear
issue. I promise I'll move on after
that.
Okay, let's nix the control part. You
you doubt that the actual control, but
there was a New York Times article
written by the by the New York Times
editor that time for national security
that that President Bush had folded in
hundreds of millions of dollars in
grants
uh to Pakistan to safeguard their
nuclear assets.
The New York Times knew about this
program, but to sit on it for a number
of months before they finally published
it. So even if they don't control it,
did they give technology to safeguard
it?
>> Most likely, yes.
>> And what would that technology be?
>> That I don't know. I I it's not my area
of expertise and I couldn't speculate,
but I will tell you that
the fact that the New York Times sat on
the article
is a way of confirming its truth.
>> Mhm.
>> And what I mean is
when one of the big outlets, the New
York Times, the Washington Post, the
Wall Street Journal,
you know, the Los Angeles Times or one
of the big broadcast news networks,
um when they
come across information like this that's
really it's big and it involves
classified information,
they always ask the White House to
confirm or to deny.
>> Mhm.
If the information is truly classified
and it's sensitive,
the National Security Advisor
will ask for a meeting. Sometimes the
meeting is with the president and the
head of the newspaper. Usually it's the
National Security Advisor.
And they'll say, "Look,
yes, it's true, but it's so sensitive
that if you publish it, it will put
lives in danger."
Almost always they'll sit on the article
until enough time passes
that people aren't in danger anymore.
The fact that they sat on the article is
confirmation that it was true.
>> Mhm. Now, let's go back to your time
when uh you were there and you caught
Abu Zubaydah.
This I'm sure you would be in line for
promotion after capturing number three
in Al-Qaeda, right?
What happened after that? What's the
story after that?
>> Well,
I got a medal.
I got a huge award.
And then I was denied promotion.
And I was shocked and I I shouted at my
boss, "What do I have to do to get
promoted around here? Do I have to catch
bin Laden? I just caught the number
three in Al-Qaeda and I'm denied
promotion?"
Well, it turned out that the reason why
I was denied promotion was that as soon
as I got home from Pakistan,
they asked me if I wanted to be trained
in the torture techniques so I could be
used to torture prisoners and I said,
"No.
I have a moral and ethical problem with
it. I believe it's illegal. I want
nothing to do with it." Of the 14 people
that they asked, I was the only one who
said no.
>> Mhm.
>> And so the the director of the
Counterterrorism Center, Jose Rodriguez,
a monster,
said that I had, his words, displayed a
shocking lack of commitment to
counterterrorism.
So,
in the meantime,
I got a
the job of a lifetime, and I became the
executive assistant to the Deputy
Director for Operations.
And
I said, I was passed over for promotion.
He said, "What?"
He said, "How?"
And I said, "Jose said that I, you know,
cuz I wouldn't torture these guys."
He said, "I'll promote you." And he just
signed a promotion. And so, I was
promoted instantly.
So, there were there were those in the
uh
>> Set up.
>> Yeah, in the chain of command that
were thinking correctly on this issue of
torture.
>> Right.
>> But, at the end of the day, they were
they were shunted aside.
And a and a decision was made that
torture was going to be an official
policy.
>> Right. And but, you blew the whistle on
it.
>> I did. You know, the the truth though is
that I I just assumed somebody else
would blow the whistle. And so, I
remained silent. And then, I resigned
from the CIA in 2004. My resignation was
effective in 2005.
And still, nobody would blow the
whistle.
And so finally, in 2007, a reporter
called me.
>> Mhm.
>> And and um I decided
I was going to do it. I was just going
to just tell the truth.
>> And
>> that's what I did.
>> And then,
one would think that you would be a hero
for free speech and blowing this whistle
blowing the whistle on this, but then
the Obama and administration,
ironically, of
campaign that was run on hope and
change, and maybe
uh should shedding some light and some
transparency,
>> Right.
>> they are the ones who actually went
ahead and prosecuted you.
>> Yes. Yes, indeed. Um, for a number of
reasons. First of all, it was John
Brennan.
Uh, John Brennan who at at first was the
Deputy National Security Advisor for
Counterterrorism and then the CIA
Director in the Obama administration. It
was John Brennan who specifically went
after me. John and I always hated each
other.
I've known John Brennan for 35 years.
I've always hated the guy. I thought he
was in over his head intellectually.
>> Yeah.
>> And um, and he was one of the founders,
one of the fathers of the of the torture
program.
And so
you had a president who had two years of
experience. Can you imagine that? You
think about that for a moment.
>> Mhm.
>> He was in the US Senate for two years.
That was his only qualification to be
President of the United States. And so
he was very susceptible
to
the advice and the biases of the people
around him. Well, John Brennan was his
lead intelligence advisor. And John
Brennan said, "We need to stop these
leaks because we're going to start doing
things like using drones to kill people.
We need to put this guy Kiriakou in
prison."
>> Right.
>> And so that's exactly what they did.
>> He didn't have any experience. He was in
Saudi Arabia as well
with when he was in the CIA, right?
>> Oh, Brennan had lots of experience.
Obama had no experience. Obama was in
the Senate for two years before he was
elected President and had never, ever
read a classified CIA document. He had
never seen one.
Yeah, utterly unprepared to become
President.
>> And what led to the eventually you
spending 24 months in jail?
I know I'm fast forwarding a bit, but
>> That's okay. Um,
what they started doing was
they knew I hadn't committed espionage.
And so the espionage
charges were dropped eventually. They
waited until I went bankrupt and then
they dropped the charges.
But um
uh what they did is they they tapped my
phones and they went through my emails,
3 years worth of emails, and they were
able to find one single email
where I confirmed the the surname of a
former colleague and they said, "Aha,
that's a crime."
And so that's the crime that I pleaded
guilty to.
So I I they offered me 30 months in
prison, I would serve 23.
And I said to my attorneys, "I'm going
to turn it down. I want to go to trial.
I haven't done anything wrong."
>> Mhm.
>> And they said that if I if I went to
trial
and I was convicted
it would be a lot longer than 23 months.
I said, "Realistically, how much time am
I looking at if I lose?"
>> Mhm.
>> They told me 12 to 18 years.
>> Yeah.
>> And so I took the deal.
>> Where would they bring the trial to? In
America?
>> Yeah, it was in the Eastern District of
Virginia and this was another thing.
>> This would be a jury in Eastern District
of Virginia. Oh, so Washington D.C.
insiders.
>> CIA,
Pentagon, FBI, DIA,
this is where they live and work. And so
that would have been my jury.
>> So the chances are that you you could
face conviction.
>> If you've ever heard of
>> Oh, yeah. If you've ever heard of O.J.
Simpson
>> Yes, of course.
>> uh he was a
So I hired O.J. Simpson's jury
consultant.
>> Okay.
>> And he we we got him a security
clearance, he went through 10,000 pages
of documents and finally we had a
meeting with all the attorneys. I had 11
lawyers
and O.J. Simpson's jury consultant. And
he said,
"If we were in any district in America
other than the Eastern District of
Virginia, I would say let's do it. We're
going to win.
But the Eastern District of Virginia,
your jury is going to be CIA, DIA, FBI,
Pentagon." He said, "You don't have a
prayer.
Take the deal."
And so I took the deal.
>> Now that you're you're out, you're
independent, and you are uh
a a commentator of a
very renowned commentator who know who
has first-hand experience, does the CIA
look at you
with some trepidation? Are they Are they
happy when you talk about all these
things? What's life after prison after
blowing the whistle and talking about
your experience?
>> Well, I still have friends inside the
CIA, and we've talked about that.
The truth is most of my detractors are
either dead or retired because uh we're
talking about, you know, my actions were
were 20 years ago.
So, um they're they're mostly dead or
retired. And now that they're retired,
nobody pays any attention to what they
say.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
the the position inside the CIA has
changed about me. Um a friend of mine
told me just a few weeks ago that she
was participating in a briefing, a
security briefing, and they showed a
slide with my picture, and it said "The
Insider Threat."
And she said everybody started booing.
Boo! Boo! And the instructor said,
"Wait. Why? Why is everybody booing?"
And she said, "He's not a threat.
He's the whistleblower.
We should aspire to be like him."
And she said in the next running of the
briefing that they had taken the slide
out.
>> That's your win.
>> I won.
It took 20 years.
>> Yeah.
>> We just did it.
>> We just celebrated Diwali over here in
India. Triumph of good over evil.
>> That's right.
>> This is it right here.
>> That's exactly right.
>> Do you So, I'm sure you're now trying to
get a pardon.
>> I am actively. Yes. And and frankly,
Donald Trump is the only president who
would have the guts to do it.
The the rest of them are just in the in
the the grasp of the CIA. I have very
very important Republicans who support
me.
Tucker Carlson,
Judge Napolitano.
Excuse me. Dr. Phil, if you know who Dr.
Phil is. Um
and and Republican political figures,
the governor of Texas, for example. And
so,
I'm told that my file is literally on
his desk.
It's just a question of whether he signs
it or not. And every day I wake up and I
say, I hope today is the day.
>> We should pray for you as well over
here.
>> Thank you so much.
>> I you I'm glad you brought up Tucker
Carlson. Cuz I was going through
his documentary series. I saw you there,
too.
>> Ah, yes.
>> Uh he ended the
the series by asking a sort of predicate
question. Just a fundamental question
about the towers that went down, the
eventual war on terror, the trillions
spent.
He asked, which countries benefited in
the end? Yes.
You you've seen it all. You lived those
years.
What's your guess?
>> Almost no countries benefited. Israel
benefited.
Um
but a lot of individuals became very
very wealthy
>> Mhm.
>> because of the so-called war on terror.
We spent more than 1 trillion dollars.
We killed as many as 2 million people.
And the ones who benefited were the
defense contractors and the intelligence
contractors.
The Eric Princes of the world and the
people at the top of organizations like
Blackwater
or the defense manufacturers, Northrop
Grumman, Lockheed Martin, Boeing.
They all got rich.
>> Right.
>> But we're we're no safer now than we
were on September 10th, 2001.
>> Mhm.
>> And we're we're we've lost
freedoms and civil liberties here in the
United States.
>> Mhm.
>> So I I'm not sure anybody really
benefited
except for those
who provided hardware and services.
>> Mhm.
>> They all got very rich.
>> May I add one thing? I feel that
Pakistan-based terror groups with a with
an eye towards India
>> they benefited. Cuz all those American
defense contractor money, that defense
parts were all
turned towards India.
>> and and I'll add something.
We paid tens of millions of dollars in
cash
as rewards
to the Pakistani intelligence service.
And God knows what they did with that
money.